This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Akshay Manchale. Today's
topic is Cloud FinOps and I have two
guests with me, JR Storment and Mike
Fuller.
JR is the executive director of the
FinOps Foundation.
He was formerly the co-founder of
Cloudability, which was later acquired
by Apptio.
He continued to work as VP of product
and engineering for a year
post-acquisition and decided to pursue
his passion of advancing the FinOps
field as a full-time employee of the
nonprofit Linux Foundation.
He has worked closely with the largest
cloud consumers in the world helping
them design strategies to optimize and
analyze their cloud spend through
technology, culture, and process.
Mike is a principal engineer and has
been working on cloud and FinOps at
Atlassian for over 10 years.
Mike's team of data engineers, analysts,
and FinOps practitioners help Atlassian
get the most value out of the money it
spends on cloud.
He holds nine AWS certifications and has
presented at multiple AWS re:Invent and
AWS Summit events on topics that include
security and cloud FinOps.
Mike has served as a member of the
FinOps Foundation Technical Advisory
Council and is currently a member of its
governing board.
JR and Mike are both co-authors of the
O'Reilly book Cloud FinOps.
JR, Mike, welcome to the show. Thanks
for having us. Thank you. It's great to
be here. JR, maybe we'll start with you
to set the context for our episode. Can
you describe what is Cloud FinOps, why
it's important?
Yeah, definitely. So, FinOps is the
practice of managing cloud spend and
specifically we're talking about public
cloud spend, big cloud providers
commonly AWS, Azure, Google Cloud. And
because of their very very variable
nature, the highly variable nature of
cloud spend, which is that comes up, it
comes down based on usage, or you pay
for what you use, and the fact that
distributed decisions are now happening
about cloud spend where engineering
teams can procure the resources they
need instantly, they can scale up new
resources, they can choose different
services. Those things coming together
really created a need for FinOps as a
discipline, which is the practice of
really understanding, allocating, and
maximizing cloud spend for companies
using it. And and when we started
talking about this a few years ago,
FinOps was really limited to just, you
know, a few set of smaller tech
companies who were practicing it using
cloud at scale, but now FinOps is
practiced kind of by every major
organization in the world, you know, as
as cloud spend as a thing has become
really vigorous and grown in the last
last few years. Great. In terms of
differences with respect to companies
that own their infrastructure, what's
different in terms of running your
business on the cloud? How does your
mental or business models for finance
change because of the cloud versus
traditional company that has its own
infrastructure? Maybe Mike? Yeah, so I
guess within the traditional
infrastructure space, you you kind of
doing these large upfront purchases that
you're depreciating over sort of a three
or five-year period. And the variation
of the spend in the data center, you're
not paying a different amount for your
equipment each time that you run. So,
what's different? Um so, yeah, with your
traditional data center, you're buying
equipment upfront with a sort of a large
upfront expenditure and then you're not
paying different amounts for your
infrastructure month by month. You're
sort of depreciating that that equipment
over a sort of a three or five-year
period, usually at sort of a fixed
depreciation schedule. Within cloud
though, you're buying servers at a per
second or even per per millisecond
basis, which means that the amount that
you're paying for your infrastructure
varies all the time. And so, the amount
of compute that you're using this second
versus the next second really does mean
that the variation of spend is what
drives a lot of the complexity. And so,
trying to apply a traditional financial
model to cloud spend means that you're
sort of waiting these long periods
between looking at at the dollars and a
lot of variation happens in between
those cycles. And so, what FinOps is
doing trying to do is really move you
into that more real-time attention to
how spend is is happening within your
organization and getting you away from
those sort of slow cadence consistent
spend financial models that are
traditionally used in the data center.
And what Mike hit on there in terms of
real-time, I should have introduced a
bit in the first part, which is the
really key thing and differentiator
with, you know, cloud and and FinOps as
compared to other previous disciplines
of managing technology is that maybe not
technically real-time, but very very
hopefully close to it, a near real-time
approach of getting consistent data in
terms of cloud spend back to those who
are responsible for using the cloud
spend so that they can use that near
real-time feedback to to change their
behavior. And that's really a key
difference is that, you know, in cloud
when you start using something, you
start paying for it. When you stop using
something, you stop paying for it. And
and that is as a fundamental model is is
very different than traditional
approaches. I think the elasticity is
really nice with the cloud where you can
get things on demand. And as an
engineer, what that enables me is to
experiment more than I could previously
with fixed infrastructure. So, sometimes
when I hear FinOps, maybe the discipline
around financial spending seems like
maybe there's more red tape that you
have to navigate as an engineer to try
something out. So, can you talk about
how it can enable or how it sustains
innovation while not completely running
loose with respect to spending and
having some sort of a framework for
that. Is that possible? Can you still
innovate while also having a disciplined
financial operating plan for the cloud?
Yeah, I definitely think so. I think
that the whole point of FinOps is to
ensure that your company maintains that
that freedom to innovate. If you look
at, you know, we've got a
a tightening sort of economic outlook at
the moment. Companies are very going
going to be looking for ways to reduce
spend. And by having a good FinOps
culture, you're able to work out where
where you're getting good value for the
spend that's being made within an
organization. And so, by being able to
sort of track the the benefits that
you're getting from the dollar spent,
you're able to then to use that that
metric to sort of encourage further
spending in areas of the for the
business. And also, it's a really about
giving confidence to the back to the
business that the the dollar spent on
innovation is returning back in business
value. And so, what what we see happen
without FinOps being in the in the
picture is that the freedom to innovate
kind of maybe gets a little bit too wild
and, you know, wastage and and
unoptimized infrastructures gets
developed. Eventually, it gets out of
sync with what the business expects to
be spending on cloud and then you end up
with these like halt moments or pull
back from cloud moments and that really
stifles innovation. So, what we're
trying to say is is a little bit of
FinOps consistently over time goes a
long way to enable innovation to stay
within the cloud space without letting
it sort of go wild and the business to
get out of sync or out of touch with
what the cloud spend should be. And so,
so it's really just finding that balance
between the company feeling very
confident with the spend that has going
into the cloud space enabling that
innovation, but also making sure that
the business feels confident that it's
been spent well. And in a lot of ways,
engineers are used to dealing with
constraints and this is just a new
constraint that's introduced and and it
can help accelerate innovation if you
get to that place where Mike's referring
to where
it's a efficiency metric, a constraint
that's introduced at the beginning. So,
it could be part of design
considerations. Where the innovation
gets hindered, I think, is if it's
introduced too late in the process or or
you're asking folks to to re-engineer
something to be more cost-efficient when
it wasn't a consideration early on. And
so, the big shift or one of the shifts
we've seen in the last few years is the
idea of cost being introduced earlier in
the process so that essentially, it's
enabling more cloud to happen and and
people thinking about cloud and cost
more on the lines of what what
additional services, higher level
innovation can you do in cloud that you
can't do in traditional models, on-prem
data centers, etc. Because you can use
different types of services, you can
procure services more quickly. And I
think, you know, the the big shift we're
we're seeing very much in that aspect is
engineers now have to consider cost as a
new efficiency metric and and therefore
operate in a new model. Mhm.
That is definitely a cultural and an
engineering mindset change, I think,
that is required to get this right. I
think that maybe the responsibility is
shared among various different functions
and businesses. So, who is involved in
Cloud FinOps? Who are the people? What
what kind of roles do different people
have to play in a sound FinOps strategy?
Yeah, there's really a big mix of
people. I'm fond of saying that everyone
is responsible for cloud cost, everyone
does FinOps, right? And so, yes,
absolutely, we're starting with the
engineers who are writing code and
deploying resources. You also have, you
know, they're now partners in finance
teams who are struggling to understand
how to allocate the cloud cost after
they come in. They're struggling to
understand how to forecast them. I was
on a call this morning with some folks
doing FinOps for government agencies and
they're their finance teams are asking
them to do five-year forecasts on their
cloud spend in a world where they're in
the middle of migrations, they've got
2,000 engineers working across different
services. It's almost impossible to do,
right? So, finance teams are thinking
about this entirely different and having
to be, you know, educated and learn and
shift. Traditionally, you had
procurement teams who had to go buy
hardware for software engineers
operations people to use. Now, they're
no longer the gatekeepers of the
hardware. They are trying to do deals
with cloud providers, make commitments
to cloud providers, buy commitment
vehicles like reserved instances or
savings plans or committed use
discounts. So, it's a complete change in
how procurement people and sourcing
people uh need to operate. You get into
product teams who have to start thinking
about their cloud costs so they can
understand how the profitability of
their individual services. And
ultimately, executives, this used to be
just a problem for those people off to
the side of the organization using a lot
of cloud. Now, you know, cloud spend is
is raised up to the level of the CFO
often because cloud spend is, you know,
the largest variable cost for many
organizations. And for a lot of the
organizations in the FinOps Foundation,
we're talking about like nine out of 10
of the the Fortune 10 large
organizations, you know, cloud is
becoming one of the biggest expenses in
the technology world after after labor,
right? After their people. And so,
really, it it has become this thing
where it's really everybody's
responsibility in the organization. You
know, all that being said, across all
those different groups, there does tend
to be a centralized enablement team, a
FinOps enablement team that is working
to help all those other groups do that.
So, Mike, Mike, what do you see? Yeah, I
think that in addition to those, uh
we're starting to see other other
personalities uh that are coming out of
like your your TBMO and your ITSM teams,
your SAM teams. They they're they're
being cloud sort of enabled engineers to
quickly and acquire licenses straight
from the cloud service provider and and
sort of skip the standard sort of SAM
teams that were there. And they're being
FinOps is able to bring that
conversation back to those uh
traditional sort of teams with
frameworks. And extending out from that,
we're seeing sustainability teams now
integrating with their data and
collaborating with FinOps teams to try
to drive this like green use of cloud
and try to bring the picture of not just
cost efficiency, but sustainable use of
cloud. So, I think that we're having a
lot of touch points from that that
central FinOps team where they can
enable a lot of different areas of the
business with the cloud spend and and
cloud billing data.
If I start from a company that has some
small footprint in the cloud, maybe they
have a roadmap to have more In your
book, you talk about the life cycle of
FinOps. So, maybe starting from that
smallish company standpoint, can you
give a broad overview of what this life
cycle of FinOps uh journey looks like?
Life cycle of FinOps which is around the
phases and I think we'll dig into those
in a moment. When it comes to the the
growth of the FinOps team within
organization from a small business up to
large, I think that that really we call
it like the adoption curve of of FinOps.
So, start from what we see happening,
especially in the smaller cloud spend
companies, is what we call the virtual
FinOps team. It's like maybe a a few key
people or maybe one or two people in the
organization that that see part of their
day job being thinking about the FinOps
related tasks. As as the cloud spend
footprint gets bigger or the complexity
of the amount of teams using cloud
within your organization grows, then
that stops becoming sort of a side gig
for someone in the organization. It
starts becoming very important to have
someone there constantly thinking about
and driving what what FinOps looks like
within your organization. So, you start
to see that FinOps practitioner role
fully evolve into a dedicated role
within the org. And then as you're
really getting to the large scale, you
know, especially when they're globally
distributed teams and that, you end up
with these, you know, full full teams of
FinOps members that are sort of
distributed different sort of capability
sets. You know, so, if things that you
we see often is things like data
engineers and analysts. The FinOps
practitioner that are just, you know,
really sort of focused in on the the
individual billing elements of of cloud
and collaborating with those finance
partners and engineering partners. JR?
Yeah, and I think we see it come from
two ways. There's a bottoms-up approach,
which is very much, I know, Mike, that's
how you started. I was just talking to
one of our members at who was a software
engineer or SRE specifically who
started, you know, in that I I see
there's a problem here. I need I need to
to go solve this. I want to help the
organization get better. And And
typically, that life cycle starts there.
And those teams work on putting in basic
FinOps practices around visibility and
allocation. But it doesn't really all
come together until you get the
combination of also a tops-down
executive support mandate. That can come
from the technology leader and ideally
should because the CTO or CIO has the
teams who are responsible for the cloud
spend. But it also typically needs to be
a partnership with the finance leaders
we talked about who needs to help drive
the importance of the overall company
numbers and the budgets and the margins
and and those areas. But ultimately, I
mean, where it's all it all heads to
over time is really enabling, you know,
more of that data-driven decision-making
by all these teams that we talked about
so they can make better decisions every
day. And a big part of that really is is
getting buy-in across the organization
that, you know, cost is important. And I
I think that's kind of the journey we
see folks go on. There's There's all the
capabilities that lead up to good
FinOps, right? There's visibility,
there's allocation, there's usage
optimization, rate optimization. But it
really means that everyone needs to
start thinking about it in a new way.
So, let's start with the initial part of
the FinOps journey where you really want
to understand what's happening in your
organization, where you're spending the
money. So, how do you how do you get
started with that? What what models do
you have to understand the cloud spend
and to analyze where you're spending
money, where you shouldn't be spending
money. How do you get started on that
journey? That then connects us to the
the FinOps life cycle, which effectively
we have sort of three phases of the
FinOps life life cycle. There's the
inform phase, which is I like to sort of
think about this as is putting the thumb
tack on the map about where you are
today. And then you have the the
optimize phase, which is really sort of
figuring out what are those paths on the
map that we could go down. Like where
could we optimize? What sort of to get
to a better position as far as our cloud
efficiency goes? What are those paths
that are available to us? And then let's
set some goals on which paths we want to
take down take ourselves down. And then
on operate phases, that's the actual
driving down the journey, taking that
that pathway. We're going to put things
into action, you know, look at
automation, implement tools, AI/ML
tools, or automation tools, or cloud
cloud vendors tooling in order for us to
start to move towards that more cloud
efficient world. And then we look back
around and go back to inform to really
check where we are. Are we are we
actually progressing down the pathway we
expected to be? Has anything sort of
thrown us off course? Come up, you know,
anomalous spend or unexpected extra
items that have sort of thrown a spanner
in the works and sort of taken us off
path. And then we just continue this
process of looping around for each of
our individual FinOps capabilities in
order to sort of measure where we are,
set where we want to be, and then
implement change to sort of head towards
that pathway. The first thing in there,
honestly, when that whole process is
just starting to look, you know, sort of
getting started. Like just starting to
look at the cloud spend data regularly.
And the one of the first things that
companies see when they start to look at
it is that it's not always clear what
the money is going to. And it's not
always clearly aligned against how the
business is structured. Now, the
business is doing reporting elsewhere,
you know, hey, we've got this set of
Amazon accounts or this set of Azure
subscriptions. And they were set up by
an engineering team, you know, maybe
when something was in a staging or
development environment and now they're
supporting some set of production spend,
too. And how do we start to tear apart,
you know, bits of the infrastructure and
make sure that we can show it back to
the people who are using it to drive
accountability, drive that
decision-making. And so, one of the
first important steps of of actually
doing FinOps is starting to get into a
tagging strategy and allocation strategy
and account strategy. Something that
that says, let's let's agree that that
this is how we're going to split out our
cloud spend so that we can then start to
build on top of that to get the rest of
the visibility we need, you know, before
we even start to think about
higher-level functions like optimizing
spend. Before we get to, you know, way
down the road to unit economics in those
areas. And I think it it it comes up. I
I feel like a broken record, but we
can't say enough like, you know, this
whole practice is really not about
spending less or saving money or
optimizing spend. I I mentioned earlier
I was on a call with this government
group and they were pushing back saying,
"Well, we're not really looking at
right-sizing or savings or any of these
things. We really just need to charge
back and show back." I mean, that's
really that first stage that majority
people find themselves at, which is how
do we understand the spend? How do we
get visibility into it? And then as you
grow, and you may have, as Mike was
saying, you know, millisecond billing or
per second billing across thousands or
millions of resources, then how do we
keep a a solid policy and governance and
strategy in place so that that spending
as it scales is still not controlled,
right? Because we don't want to control
and lock down spending to the earlier
point of not hindering innovation, but
that there's a there's a strategy to
keep it allocated and keep visibility in
place as it gets to be really big. You
mentioned chargeback and showback to
understand what's happening with your
cloud bill. So, do you just get a large
PDF with your spending maybe right now?
But you want to like improve on that
process. So, can you describe how you
improve on that process from just having
one large account, maybe at one bill, to
getting this chargeback or showback sort
of a model to understand your cloud
spend? Yeah, so the the data that you
get and Mike, I'm going to pass to you
in a minute to get your your take on how
you started with it. But the the data
that you get, right? And you say PDF,
yeah, that may be your invoice, which is
the PDF of of billing at the end, which
is going to be rolled up to a service
level and maybe
some number of dozens of pages, but the
underlying data, the granular detail of
the individual resources, in Google,
it's the big query export. In AWS, it's
the cost and usage report. That data can
be hundreds of millions or billions of
individual charges for a large company
at scale in cloud. So, the challenge
steps back a bit to not even be, you
know, can you start to understand this,
but can you even open and use the data?
Like a lot of companies need to use the
cloud in order to open the cloud bill in
order to get insights out of it. So, how
did you all approach it? Mike, as you
can start getting that more detail.
Yeah, it's kind of like you you know,
when I started the cloud bill for us was
you know, a couple of million lines and
and today we're in the billions of lines
and so the complexity of that is we've
we've been asking for more detail as
practitioners over the years cuz we need
more detail in order to get the the
granularity in order to understand the
cost and also to allocate those costs
out to teams. That's a sort of a a
double-edged sword there where we ask
for the detail, you get the detail, the
detail then adds to those little billing
lines and really expands out the the
breadth and depth of the data. But the
benefit of having that level of detail
is you are able to individually identify
nearly every cloud resource individually
that's costing you money every hour and
allocate it through the teams. Now,
there's a decision between chargeback
and showback and this seems to be really
driven by the choice of the company.
Some companies like to have a central
budget of IT and so they really do
charge it to a central location and the
benefit there would be for showback to
be able to allow the teams that are
causing that spend to be able to still
see the impact of their their decisions
without having to worry about
distributing you know, budgets out to
teams that know you know, previously
hadn't had that that experience. For
companies that have already got
distributed budgets across the
organization, then it becomes really
important that they get the cost from
this central bill in the PDF as you put
it out to those teams budgets so that
they're actually reflected at the right
places on the P&L. So, it's really the
decision between chargeback and showback
is an org level usually finance team
level decision, but the the value you
get of either is the same thing which is
the right the teams that are actually
driving the spend are able to actually
see that and and put that back to those
decisions they're making. Is is that
cost increased by the the the change we
made last week actually worth that much
money or should we be thinking about
rolling it back or does that actually
land where we thought it was going to
land in you know, in costs? So, you
know, there's a whole pile of next layer
challenges you get with things like
shared services and that, but showback
and chargeback is is very key to that
surfacing the cost to the right teams at
the right time. Do you have an example
where either chargeback showback has
resulted in better utilization that you
can share? Yeah, so I think we talk
about the Prius effect. So, effectively
the idea here is is that when you
surface the costs to a team that they
they naturally want to optimize that
anyway. So, you know, the Prius effect
sort of talks about the transition from
the 1970s car that's guzzling gas down
the freeway in order for you to figure
out the efficiency, you kind of wait
until you run out of petrol and then you
can back calculate the the miles that
you got on the tank. You go to a more
modern electric vehicle, it tells you
that immediately on the dashboard sort
of the exact amount of kilowatts that
are coming out of the battery. And what
usually tends to happen is people just
drive more efficiently just because
they're being made aware of of the
impact of their driving and it's it's
easier for them to make those choices as
they're making it. Do do I really want
to put the foot down cuz I'm running
late or do I am I okay to take a second
longer and be more efficient? And so,
the same sort of thing happens with with
engineering teams that if they're aware
of the cost impacts of those decisions,
then naturally they will adjust the
decisions they're making and correct the
decisions they've made based on that
feedback loop. And so, the tighter you
can get that between the decision
they've made and the time they are able
to be informed on it, the quicker they
can identify the driver of of the cost
changes and and adjust as needed. And
so, yeah, we definitely feel like this
is one of the real key points for that
near near real-timeness and why having a
chargeback showback model combined with
that that's fast feedback loop really
helps with driving efficiency for for
engineering. Do you think that sometimes
if you react too quickly to seeing what
your spend is and maybe you reduce your
instance size or maybe you make some
modifications, does that lead to
problems with respect to peak periods
where you have massive loads? How do
teams deal with that or when you start
showing teams what they're spending, how
do you prevent them from taking actions
that might be detrimental to the
business itself? I think this comes down
to cloud experience. Like your
engineering teams will need to
understand their workloads in cloud, not
just the point in time what the workload
looks like right this hour, but what it
looks like over time. And I I feel like
this is just a standard SRE reliability
problem. Even if you take cost out of
the picture, you know, they're going to
look at ways that they scale up is scale
up times fast enough? Do they have
enough capacity to to be able to scale
up to the right sizes for for the peak
workloads? Really, I think this is that
sort of handhold where it is on the
engineers to help us pick where they can
they can be more efficient, but also
it's on them to sort of balance between
good and fast and cheap. So, we call
this the iron triangle and it's it's
effectively like you can spend more and
make a really good really fast really
reliable service or you can spend less
and make some compromises in those
elements. So, you might be having you
know, only two AZs not three or you
might be only running in one region and
not two. And it's really on each of
those services that you're running for
your business to to balance which of
those you're going to invest heavier in
and which one is actually okay. Do it
does it need to be fault tolerant or can
it just be highly available because it's
an internal service or a lower tier
service. So, that balance really is it's
up to engineering teams to learn this
experience and make sure that they're
thinking about that balance between
good, fast and cheap. There's a nice
intersection with SRE performance and
all of that like you said. I want to
talk about the organization structure
and what your business actually sells,
right? So, you might have a product that
is
running and you have to have
infrastructure to run that. Maybe you're
a company that has multiple product
lines that have shared services. How
does the chargeback showback model work
in that sort of a model where you have
different products that have their own
infrastructure requirements and you also
have these shared services that
different products end up using, right?
Maybe there's a log storage thing or
something like that. So, how do those
companies account for those shared costs
and how does the chargeback or showback
model work in that sort of a situation?
Yeah, so I guess with the the difference
between a single product company and a
multi-product company, I think that
that's a a nice banner to put over top
of things, but the reality is as as more
and more engineering moves towards
microservices, even the single product
teams have many different services
running internally. Some of those will
be to support the internal reporting
like you say, logging, observability
infrastructure. Some of them will be
there to run the actual production
service you're offering. And then in the
multi-product companies, you have
multiple products that are aligned and
sharing services between them or you
might have actually separate arms of the
business, one running the the
distribution center and one running
delivery centers and stuff like that.
So, the idea that there are some
companies out there with just the simple
one thing in the cloud, it's only ever
short-lived because as you do more and
more business more and more of your
business in cloud, you end up with this
sort of complex mix of things and then
so, that then gets us to the whole
shared resources or shared services. And
so, you kind of I feel put them in two
two separate buckets. There's like a
single cloud resource that's being
shared and a group of cloud resources
being shared and more often than not you
end in the group. So, you think of
something like a Kubernetes cluster, you
end up with more than one instance, you
know, many storage volumes, load
balancers. You have all these sort of
cloud resources. So, the first part of
shared shared service cost reporting is
to first identify what is the thing
you're sharing as a cloud resources set.
And so, that's where your tagging and
account strategies are going to come in.
Making sure you're putting all the
things in in a project or in a
subscription in order for you to
identify the the thing you're sharing
amongst your teams. And then the thing
the cloud service provider can't give
you in the billing data is what's what
is on those those shared resources. So,
within a Kubernetes clusters, who are
the teams that are running particular
workloads? And so, that that's then when
you come into what we call the
proportion data. And so, this is
something you collaborate with with the
teams that are running those shared
resources or shared services to try and
get that extra layer of data that you
need from them to understand which teams
are using how much of that shared
resource over time. And then the two
pieces together, the cloud bill with the
collection of cloud resources in
identifying what you're trying to share
and then that proportion data saying
which teams to give the cost of that
much of the infrastructure to. And by
doing that, you're able to then take a
you know, a large cloud spend that's
being shared across potentially hundreds
of teams and actually break that out and
show those teams or even charge back to
those teams the individual cloud costs
for those resources. And this shared
service issue is is one of the main
challenges that we see out there in
terms of getting to the full allocation,
getting to forecasting and getting
accountability out there. You know, Mike
mentioned Kubernetes as an example. You
know, it's it's not just shared
services, it's layers of virtualization,
right? That are being split out in cloud
as one layer of virtualization,
Kubernetes is another on top of that.
And so, we we do see that as being a big
hole in early stage practices which is
not properly accounting for those. And
then ultimately something that you know,
a lot of effort is put into. I think he
talked about the proportional split of
the spend. I mean, ultimately where that
allocation of spend is heading toward is
is also then measuring the proportional
output that each one is getting, right?
Like what activity is it actually
generating ultimately, maybe even what
revenue is it driving, you know, what
what what is the and that's how the
whole point of this whole practice,
right? Is okay, so let's not just look
at what we're spending in cloud, but
let's look at the value that's coming
back out on the other end from that from
that shared service so that we can start
to you know, make some trade-off
decisions. Mike mentioned the iron
triangle. Spending more isn't
necessarily a bad thing if you are
trying to get better performance, if
you're trying to drive more customers,
if you're trying to deliver you know,
more features and more innovation. So,
getting that shared services in place,
you know, I think or the reporting of it
is is really key, right? To getting the
larger bit in place for allocating and
showing back to get to that unit
economic view of things. You both
mentioned about tagging in accounts. So,
can you maybe dig into that a little bit
to say what options are available to be
able to group your utilization into your
business unit, into your products, into
your teams, etc. How do you enforce
that? How do you set that cultural
expectation maybe to be able to at a
later point look and attribute your
resource utilization? Yeah, so I guess
the most granular weapon in in the
process there is that the account level
hierarchy. So, your accounts, your
subscriptions, your projects. That's
sort of larger cloud resource like a
cloud account that you're putting your
resources within. And so, you're wanting
to sort of define a strategy around
those that allows you to sort of at a
granular level understand the
infrastructure that goes inside. So, the
obvious ones are dev, stage, and prod,
right? You're you're not sort of mixing
the the three together in one project or
whatever. Then within that you'll
probably end up with multiple of
something. So, two different services or
four or five shards of a single service.
You wanting to be able to identify which
of those cloud resources are part of
which piece. And so, that's where your
tags and labels come into to sort of
start to separate the two. With tags and
labels you've got a lot more more
granularity. You can put a lot of those
on cloud resources. Obviously with that
balance of trying to get them done
properly by your teams, which we'll get
to in a second. That tag and label
really is the the more granular piece.
So, you're taking that large the sort of
real coarse grain account level and then
getting down to those granular level
tags and accounts and then the the
combination of the two. Lastly, there's
what we call a synthetic tag. So, when
we get the cloud billing, we're using
detail in that cloud bill with some
external lookup, some extra piece of
data. And so, this is where you're
getting a lot of the CMDBs type lookups
happening where we're bringing in extra
information we know. So, we're using one
key piece of information maybe like the
service name of a cloud resource to pull
in extra data after the fact into the
cloud bill. And that gives you even more
granularity to the details about
individual cloud resources. The the
trick there obviously is to make sure
that your teams are building their
resources in the right cloud accounts
and are tagging and labeling which you
mentioned. And so, there's sort of I
guess there's sort of three approaches
that we see to that. There's the control
of what can be done. And and we're
starting to see the CSPs or the cloud
service providers now offer more
features around preventing the creation
of resources without the right tags and
tag values. Now, these are they're not
perfect. It's not a perfect silver
bullet today. You know, there's only
certain ways you can describe particular
characteristics of that. And potentially
that would impact existing running
deployments, etc. in your in your
environment. So, it's not an easy switch
to turn on, but it is a great area for
you to start to put some controls around
tagging and labeling.
After that then you have the sort of
remediation type tools that come in and
they might stop cloud resources if
they're not tagged correctly or you
know, we see that sort of going towards
deletion of cloud resources. And that
sort of that's really a hard one for for
some companies to take on, especially if
you know that it potentially could
delete real production stuff. And so,
there's an adoption curve of that sort
of control after the fact. And then the
lastly, which is the more softer
approach, which is just to at least
report upon to teams where they are
tagged correctly, where they're not
tagged correctly, and having allocation
methods that handle for untagged
resources. So, that you know when it's
not tagged, this is how it's handled
that it someone will ultimately end up
responsible for it. You know, when you
end up with no sort of remediation
action at the end, you end up with a lot
of costs that just fall in a hole where
no one's paying attention to them. And
that's worse than just having a you
know, a fairly crude allocation method
would give it to somebody to care about.
You know, usually once you tell somebody
that they're getting cloud costs that
are not theirs, they usually want to
figure out whose whose are they and get
them allocated to them properly. So,
you're sort of distributing that that
pain point of unallocated costs. I guess
the clarity around your spending
improves over time to a point where you
have very fine processes in place to
always attribute correctly, catch
attributions that are not present for
whatever reason. I wanted just dig into
one other point you mentioned was the
challenges with tagging, labeling with
respect to virtualization. When you have
another layer of virtualization like
Kubernetes that's orchestrating your
containers, that's running in different
machines that are already virtualized.
Can you talk a little bit about what is
the challenge there and what do you
recommend that teams and companies can
do in those situations? The funny thing
with Kubernetes is it's it's kind of a
cloud on top of a cloud. And you end up
applying all the same FinOps practices
again to the layer above. And so, you
start to then think about namespaces
just like you thought about cloud
accounts. You know, your projects as
projects and subscriptions. That's your
namespace. And within the namespace you
can then label the pods. And they're
kind of your your parallel to the tags
that you had within the cloud resources
above. And so, you can kind of apply yet
again the same coarse and and fine grain
allocation strategies that you had at
the raw cloud account into the
Kubernetes environment. I guess a
well-written tagging labeling strategy
or policy within your organization can
almost be just completely translated
straight one-for-one into the Kubernetes
land. And then you can apply very
similar sort of things. Like you can
prevent pods from starting unless
they've got the right labels. You can
stop or you know, terminate pods that
don't have the correct labeling. So, you
can almost apply all the same strategies
that you had at the cloud layer again in
the Kubernetes. When you go over away
from something like Kubernetes into to
other things like EMR jobs or shared
database layers, potentially similar
sorts of things. But you know, you you
might be able to tag and label or to
namespace particular things. Is the
metering of your usage that could be
done in one way of for on the cloud
provider, whereas Kubernetes might meter
and tell you how much you're using for a
particular pod, container, whatever in
different ways. So, does that translate
well when you apply the same tags and
labels across both sides? Yeah, so I
guess it's the tags and labels really
just identify the the workload itself.
So, whether it's raw on the cloud
account or within something like a
Kubernetes pod. To figure out which is
which, the metering of which is
important for your proportioning is
really driven by the the workloads
themselves. Some might be very CPU
intensive and so, you're really wanting
to use that measure as far as what is
the impact. So, if you're finding that
you've got very low CPU pods, but
they're using a lot of memory, that's
probably going to be your driver. The
more of those you need, the more cloud
underlying cloud resources that are
needing to be provisioned. So, it's
really trying to identify what is the
driving element of the workload and then
using that to measure. We've seen
workloads that are driven mostly by
network activity. Large amounts of
network activity, very little amount of
CPU. And so, you kind of for those
you're starting to look at how much of
the network capacity is it using as a as
a proportion of the the cluster. And so,
yeah, I think it really you can't have
one sort of silver bullet that does them
all. It's kind of really looking at
workload specific what is the driving
element.
And the the principles are the same
within a container world in some ways.
It's like a it's another little FinOps
cycle that happens within containers,
right? You asked about the allocation
strategies. You know, instead of
allocating out to tags, instead of
allocating you know, to projects in
Google and those things. Yeah, you are
allocating to namespaces and you know,
you're looking at at labeling in the
within the container system. But then
you also have the same issue. We talk
about shared costs of allocating out not
only the use of the containers
themselves, but also like unused
portions of it, right? And there there's
you add another layer of right-sizing
has to happen within you know, the
containers themselves, within the
cluster, you know, what hardware that
cluster is sitting on. And there's sort
of recursive layers of this. And and
that becomes an issue of organizational
challenge because again, you're
distributing duty duties rather between
different people, right? There might be
one group managing the containers and
the cluster, another managing
infrastructure in some cases, another
who's managing the commitments to the
cloud providers that are running the
resources that are running all these
things. And so, you've got to loop
through all of those, right? And and
sort of start at again, where is the
spend going within the containers? And
then how are we using the right amount
of it? And then how can we get a better
rate for that which we are using? And
then be constantly communicating that
out in that real-time feedback loop. So,
that you're you're not doing these big,
"Hey, we see spend is really off and we
need to cut down and make changes."
You're doing constant iterative
iterations to make sure that you're
point of continuing to the cycle
constantly and regularly. Mhm. I want to
switch gears into what comes after being
in this inform phase where you have a
mature information reporting strategy
where you can charge back, show back to
various business units, engineering
teams what they're using. So, the next
real thing is optimization. And in the
book you talk about two different levers
that are generally available for
optimizing. Can you talk about what they
are and then we'll dig into them? Yeah,
so the the two levers or levers are
essentially paying or using less, which
is your usage optimization lever, and
then paying less, which is your rate
optimization lever. And there's no no no
magic here. And and kind of like
everything else, there's there's a usage
quantity and a rate quantity. But what's
different in FinOps world is really I
think who is responsible for those and
the fact that it is so distributed.
Historically, folks when they're
starting to jump into FinOps, they think
pretty much immediately, you've even
mentioned it earlier, right-sizing. I
know I I want I want to I want to
right-size the the thing to do the the
job that it's is needing to be done.
That's a really important, you know,
lever to pull in terms of, you know, say
a compute resource and getting the
right-size instance against that. But
you kind of want to go back before that
to say, "Hey, I how do I just turn off
things that, you know, aren't being used
at all, right?" There's a there's a
shutting those down. That type of work,
that usage optimization work, really is
best done by the engineering teams and
the operations teams who are responsible
for that infrastructure and understand
how those changes may impact performance
down the road. So, very much in FinOps,
we want to push the data out to those
teams to think about where they
potentially use less. On the other side
of that, there's how do we pay less for
what we have used or are using, and
that's really the rate optimization
piece tends to live in the more advanced
practices within a centralized FinOps
team who is looking across the entire
cloud estate, the entire cloud
infrastructure, to figure out how to
make broad commitments to a cloud
provider. Hey, we think we're going to
use about this much in the coming year.
So, we're going to work with the cloud
provider around a commitment there. And
in the microcosm, looking to say, "Hey,
this team is using this much of this
particular resource. Let's make a 1 or
3-year commitment via reserved instance
or a savings plan." And what what's
interesting there about that that second
lever is that we we do see it
centralized very often because, you
know, the teams who are who are
deploying resources and writing code,
you know, are trying to right-size or
optimize the usage, they're not often
thinking about those financial
commitments to the cloud provider. And
And frankly, it sometimes they're afraid
to say, "Yeah, I'm going to use I'm
doing air quotes, you know, this
resource for the next year or 3 years
because they're looking at cloud as
something that they may want to use the
latest resource type and they may want
to use a new service that's come out.
Whereas, a central team who's
responsible for the entire
organization's spend can say, "Yeah, you
know, generally, as an organization,
we're using this many thousands or
millions of dollars a month within this
cloud provider across lots of different
teams that may be changing what they're
doing constantly. So, we're comfortable
as a larger organization committing to
this amount of this type of resource or
this amount of spend." And so, those two
things, obviously, are very closely
interconnected. As you get into things
like forecasting of spend, it gets even
more complicated because you have to
start to, you know, think about scenario
modeling around
not only what you're using, but if this
team makes this optimization to the
usage, how does that affect our
commitments to the cloud provider? And
those commitments affect the rates,
which obviously affect, you know, how
much you're going to spend over time.
So, it's a fine dance between the two.
One of the things that we often get
asked as well is which of those levers
should you should pull first, right?
Should you optimize the usage or should
you optimize the rates? And and people
commonly say, "Well, of course you want
to optimize the usage. I want I want to
turn off things I'm not using and want
to size down things that are too large.
Why would I make any commitments to the
cloud provider before I do that?" And
unfortunately, the the
the stark reality of the the case often
is that those those changes to the
infrastructure can take a lot of time
and a lot of effort by engineering
operations teams. And often the the
right approach is is really to start
making commitments while you're
optimizing usage, right? To commit to
reserved instances, save savings plans,
those things so that in parallel, you
can be optimizing your usage efficiency
while you're getting better rates for
what you're already using. In terms of
right-sizing,
there are these developments with
serverless offerings, right? Where
you're constantly only paying for what
you use rather than predicting what you
might need on a box and then using it
mostly at some fixed capacity most of
the time. So, how does that impact your
general forecasting or understanding of
cloud spend? Does it make it easier or
does it complicate things for the FinOps
journey? Some people see serverless as
some like solution to not needing to
right-size. And the reality of it is is
that you're still sizing your
serverless, you know, whether it's a
function as a service, you're picking a
memory or CPU commitment that you're
getting for that function. Or if it's a,
you know, serverless-based
container or orchestration like EKS or
any of the Kubernetes or ECS services,
you're sizing those pods. And so, you're
making some form of size commitment even
with a serverless in most cases. And so,
you didn't really avoid the
right-sizing, you've just changed the
the sort of how it's sized from being a,
you know, size of a EC2 instance or a VM
instance to really the size of the the
serverless commitment you're making. I
think that once you often the sort of
right-sizing for serverless is put on
the lower priority because for the vast
majority of cloud spenders, it's VM
instances, managed databases, and object
storage that are like your three big
items. And so, serverless usually is a
way down the list as far as cost goes on
your bill. But I think that as we see
more and more companies lean heavier
into serverless, it will start to become
more of a cost item on their bill and
and right-sizing serverless workloads
will start to become way more popular
because, you know, it becomes more and
more predominant in their cloud bill.
And then as far as predicting though,
like I think the good thing about
serverless is you run a lot of it. Like
it's your big cloud spenders would be
running tens if not hundreds of
thousands of EC2 instances. When you run
enough of them, you end up with this
sort of like very stable base load
amount of with serverless, you're cuz
it's such a small individual element,
even small cloud consumers using
serverless use a lot of serverless. And
so, you end up with that base load very
quickly anyway. And so, predicting the
workloads on serverless, I think will
become easier because you'll end up with
lots of teams doing lots of different
things with serverless, but in
aggregate, a fairly stable base load.
There's going to be huge spikes at
periods, but you kind of end up with
this like if you think about sort of a
sine wave and then a second sine wave
face sort of face-shifted, while one
team is using a lot, another team is
using less, and then while that they
they're using a lot, the other one's it.
So, you sort of end up with this sort of
like noise all canceling out in sort of
this like sort of hum, if you will, of
the cloud spend ticking along. So, but
yeah, like
it's interesting that in I think it will
be interesting as more and more teams
become more cloud-native with cloud
adopting more and more of these
serverless things to how that sort of
story fleshes out over the next couple
of years. Yeah, that makes sense about
how they might normalize out depending
on time of day and different services.
We talked earlier about different
organizations having shared services or
rather everyone's looking at
microservices and how lots of resources
are in fact shared.
In terms of rate optimization,
how do you go about getting the number
of reserved instances or getting a
committed usage discount from a cloud
provider and then applying it back into
the actual products or the actual needs
of the infrastructure? How does How do
you map that into individual products
and resources? Yeah, this is a an
interesting challenge. It's different at
various stages of maturity. Right? So,
early on, the challenge when you're
starting a FinOps practice is you're
you're beginning to make commitments
to the cloud provider for reserved
instance capacity or savings plan
capacity, and it's a small percentage of
your total spend. And what companies end
up with is a big deviation between the
on-demand spend and what you're paying
for that and the covered or reserved
spend and what you're paying there. And
one of the challenges across most of the
cloud providers is you generally can't
really dictate where those savings are
applied. They're applied to a certain
type of resource in a certain region,
but you can't say this particular
resource. And they're not really meant
to be tied to an individual resource,
they're meant to be tied to a type of
spend.
And so, early on, there can be big
differences in how an individual team
sees their spending because they're
either getting that discount or not. And
longer term though, as you get to a a
very large scale of good coverage in
those areas, and let's say, you know,
90% of your coverable resources are
covered, the the challenge changes a
bit, which is that you're kind of
instead of having to figure out who's
going to get who's not, you're trying to
figure out can you cover that last
remaining bit, right? To get them to the
next level of of discounting. And so,
yeah, it's I mean, it's a hard problem.
You've been through years of it, Mike.
How have you sort of seen it evolve?
Yeah, for the most part, I think that
the, as you say, the higher level
coverage gives us a fairly stable rate
that teams can then sort of trust upon.
But there there is times where
particular workloads really kind of miss
out on being the one that gets covered.
And that's often the case with things
like savings plans, they often want to
discount the highest return items first.
So, you've got teams that are kind of
running those smaller size instances,
potentially in in the more common
regions. And so, they end up kind of
being the team that always misses out.
And so, there there this sort of
conversation of reallocating the savings
does come up from time to time. I know
that there's tooling in this space from
from third-party vendors that can help
you reallocate some of the savings. One
of the approaches we I've taken
previously is we we actually scrape back
all of the savings from a particular
product line and then reallocate the the
dollars on budget lines as we want to
apply it as a sort of more, you know,
more fair system, if you will. And then
I have seen in-house tooling being built
by some of our our best, most advanced
practitioners that will reshuffle and
allocate these RIs to different teams as
they needed. So, it it's really it just
comes down to the the amount of
importance that it is that the RI
savings hits the right team, so the
materiality of that. And then the amount
of effort you really want to put into
reallocating that saving for that
particular area of the business. In the
most part, with the higher level
coverage, you end up with just the small
sort of pockets not not getting the
right benefit, and you might be able to
just adjust that with some added budget
in that business unit, that sort of
thing. Increasingly, we're seeing a
trend as well where some of the more
advanced FinOps practices are actually
not even paying attention to where
the discount is being applied and are
setting essentially their internal rates
of we're we're managing that coverage of
commitments centrally, and if you use
this type of resources, we're going to
give you this type of rate for it. And
then they're, as Mike said, sometimes
they're shuffling behind the scenes or
they're doing kind of a second set of
books. There's the actual cloud billing
data, and then there's how that's
allocated internally. And whether that's
the right approach or or wrong, it's
presents different set of challenges. I
presume the second set of books kind of
accounts for normalizing the cost across
different teams. For example, if I'm a
team It does. that happens to get like
reserved instances or discounted
instances all the time, my total spend
looks lower than it should be, right?
So, going back into the inform phase of
understanding where you're spending and
how much you're spending, your second
rate of books that you just mentioned,
is is that the reason being that you can
normalize the actual cost of the
underlying resource across different
rates applied to the exact same instance
type or service that you're buying. And
if you think about that feedback loop
and the pre-sales effect that Mike
mentioned, it's much more effective when
you see spend that you can influence and
that you know that your action is going
to change that, right? Because And so,
we're seeing a lot of these companies
that are doing this second set of books
say, "What in consumer of cloud engineer
engineering team, don't worry about what
rate you're potentially going to get.
Just focus on using the right amount at
first lever. And then, we'll get you the
best possible rates for that." And it it
it removes this this scenario that
happens a lot unfortunately in those
earlier stages adoption where one day a
team gets a reserved instance assigned
and their prices are low. And then, they
shut down a resource. And while they
have it shut down, another team picks up
that discount. It goes to the team. They
bring a resource back online. And
suddenly, their their rates have gone up
and they say, "Well, I haven't I haven't
changed anything. I'm using you maybe I
may even be using smaller resources or
fewer resources and my bill has gone up.
And so, that's why we're seeing that
move towards separating those out. This
becomes really important for things like
MSPs that that want to have a standard
stable rate for the what the services
they're charging out to their customer
base. And you see tools like Amazon
billing conductor are sort of really
supporting this model of sort of
standardizing the rates presented within
the billing data. And sort of in
italics, hiding the savings in order for
you to sort of allocate them yourself
where you where you need it. Mhm. It's
interesting that everyone is working
towards that sort of common
understanding of where your spend is
going. It's not just from your end but
it's also from the cloud providers that
are assisting and evolving their billing
data to suit this sort of like
allocation. Once you're in this journey
where you have your information
necessary, you have the optimizations,
you understand what you can do. You talk
about just the operational phase, like
where you operate with this framework.
Can you talk about what sort of advanced
strategies and techniques exist once
you're past the initial set of
low-hanging fruits to move towards a
more sound financial operating strategy
for the cloud? Yeah, like the the
ultimate goal that we see for FinOps is
to get into that data-driven
decision-making. And so,
there's a whole pile of different
capabilities within FinOps that can of
kind of deliver you towards that
ultimate goal of decision-making. And
we've covered a lot of the sort of the
bread and butter capabilities today.
We've mentioned forecasting a couple of
times. It's also another really
important one, which often connects with
budgeting. But integration with other
frameworks is also really important for
for FinOps to fully settle into the
business and and sort of mesh well with
the existing practices that are there.
But ultimately, yeah, like if FinOps is
done well, engineers don't see FinOps as
as an added task. It's not oil and
water. It's it's just mixed into the way
they think about cloud.
And the way they they're making their
decisions and getting that feedback loop
happening is almost a natural behavior
for engineering. So, there's a whole
pile of capabilities that we cover in
the FinOps framework on the finops.org
website that really sort of cover each
of those areas and what they look like
at a at a starting phase of those
capabilities right through to advanced
what we're seeing it as an advanced
practitioner
out in the field. And so, the
capabilities aren't really a checklist.
They're more like a a menu of items that
you can pick to build the right practice
for the right organization. And I think
the the first early days of of FinOps
really lived in a world where FinOps was
in a bubble. It was
billing data spend data that was really
organizations or people in your state
had to go find and they had to go look
for and they had to think about it. Oh,
our costs are up. I need to go check
this out. And and where it's moved for
more advanced organizations is that you
know, the data of FinOps is in the path
of the engineers. It's in the path of
the executives. It's in the path of
everyone who needs it. So, it's not
outside their workflow. And this
manifests in a tangible basis in taking
FinOps and cost-related data and putting
it into engineering tools into Grafana
where they're looking, into Jira where
they're collecting when planning
sprints, into wherever they're working.
And the other side of that also is
starting to integrate in other data with
Mike mentioned intersection with other
frameworks. Integrating in other types
of data revenue data business output
data, all of these things. Because
costing in its own is really hard for
folks to I think understand when you're
dealing with an organization that may be
spending millions, hundreds of millions,
billions of dollars in technology spend,
what is the right amount of spend? How
much is too much or too little? And so,
you really want to get into a place
where you're combining that with other
business data to give context to that
information. And then, making sure as we
talked about, it's early on in the
process. Oddly, the most advanced
organizations, what they're doing is
nothing magical. What they're they're
considering FinOps data at the beginning
of the architectural design process
rather than the end, right? And that's
letting them actually make an effect
change throughout that process. And
they're not asking engineers to go out
of their workflows. And they're they're
aligned in in their outputs to say,
"Yeah, we're we're going to make
decisions about cost that ultimately
you're going to result in better
outcomes at all stages of the process
rather than trying to wedge in last
minute a change that's going to reduce
costs and may have a negative impact on
business outcomes."
I want to just wrap up with one thing,
but I think you touched upon this
already in your previous response, but
what are the right cultural expectations
that you can set as a business leader?
What not to do in terms of controlling,
understanding, and optimizing your cloud
spend? Any last closing thoughts on that
for leaders to set that expectation, set
that cultural workflow in in terms of
having a sound FinOps strategy? I've got
one I can start with, Mike, and then
I'll give one to you. But for me, one of
the big differences we saw from the
first version of the Cloud FinOps book
to the second one and after a couple
years of looking at it, was just how
often people who are new to the practice
and in the early days of this, they
would go to engineering teams and sort
of be blaming them. They would be an us
versus them approach of "You need to cut
costs. You're being wasteful. Here's all
these recommendations to save money.
You're not doing your job." And that
immediately puts an engineer or anybody
on their back foot and makes them want
to push back and and and disagree and
have an argument. And the the really
advanced and successful folks are are
using basic human motivation skills to
partner, right? In the organization to
to come in with with data to have a
conversation to say, "Hey, how can I
help look at this with you and come to
the best outcome on their own." And and
I think that's that's really the most
important learning from seeing a lot of
folks fail
Yeah, I maybe to put a bit of a spin on
it thinking about sort of economic
outlooks and and potential downturns and
stuff like that, it'd be easy for CTO
leaders to set that tone for the
engineering teams to go and solve the
cost problem or, you know, go reduce
spend. You end up with a lot of people
moving a lot of bricks all at the same
time and you don't know if you're
building a better cloud or you're
actually making it worse. So, really I
feel like just understanding that this
is a like JR says, it's a partnership.
It's a collaboration between teams. So,
everybody is building towards the same
awesome outcome for the organization and
you don't end up with everybody trying
to help without talking to each other. I
think that if there's just a tendency
for not so much like a role separation,
everyone understands their role they
play and they all want to play together
in the same sandpit, that really helps
drive a good outcomes for the for the
business. Great. Thank you so much, JR
and Mike, for coming on the show and
talking about Cloud FinOps. This was
really nice and informative to
understand how and what not to do with
respect to cloud spending. This is
Akshay Manchali for Software Engineering
Radio. Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at se-radio.
slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.